Hi again. In previous courses,
we've discussed the
importance of breaking
your project down into milestones
and tasks and assigning
those tasks to different
members of your team.
We've also discussed setting
a schedule and budget.
But once the project
execution phase gets going,
how do you actually know that
the work is getting done?
Well, you can do this in a
few ways, but primarily,
you can keep tabs on
project progress by
tracking and measurement.
This is actually a big part
of project management.
Tracking, by definition,
is a method of
following the progress of
a project's activities.
Measuring project performance
regularly to identify deviations
from the project plan can help
ensure that the project
stays on track.
A deviation is anything that
alters your original
course of action.
Deviations from the project plan
can be positive or negative.
Are you ahead of schedule
because a technical problem
is less complex than you
estimated? Thumbs up.
Did a natural disaster shut
down your testing team?
Big thumbs down.
Both of these are
examples of deviations.
They're also examples
of why tracking is
such a crucial part of your role
during the project
execution phase.
Let's examine some
of the ways that
tracking is beneficial for
your project's success.
To start, tracking makes
key project information
transparent, and transparency is
essential for accurate
decision-making.
Even the strongest
project managers make
poor decisions when they
lack information or context.
Tracking centralizes
project information so that
everyone can
understand the status
of each part of the project,
which can then help you identify
gaps in your knowledge.
Also, projects have so
many little details.
It's hard to keep
everything straight.
Tracking helps ensure that
you don't risk
forgetting something.
Second, tracking helps keep
all team members and stakeholders
in touch with
deadlines and goals.
To ensure that everyone has
visibility into project progress,
you should have a
project plan that
works both for you and your team.
This way you're all
on the same page
about how the project
is progressing.
You will learn about
different ways to
track a project later
in this module.
Tracking is also
crucial for recognizing
risks and issues that can
derail your progress.
With effective tracking, you will
be able to identify issues in
a timely fashion and work with
your team to take
corrective action.
By providing visibility into
the various parts of the project,
tracking helps you and your team
identify and focus
on areas at risk.
And finally, tracking helps
build confidence that
the project is set to
be delivered on time,
in-scope, and within budget.
Having a clear, up-to-date
picture of the overall
project status
keeps the team motivated and
focused on staying the course.
So to recap, tracking
is important for
a few key reasons,
like transparency,
risk management, and keeping
the project on track.
Coming up, we'll take you
through some of the key items to
track during project
execution. Meet you there.